Guide to the Rupert Wildt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Rupert Wildt papers
1876-1981
MS 800
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.5
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, notes and offprints documenting Rupert Wildt's career as a professor in the Yale University department of astronomy (1946-1976), president of the Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy (1965-1968) and as visiting lecturer at universities in the United States and abroad.
Wildt, Rupert, 1905-1976
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Rupert Wildt, 1977.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1946-1974. II. Organizations, 1949-1981. III. Personal Papers, 1898-1968. IV. Writings, 1928-1972. V. Writings of Others, 1876-1974.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, organizational files, notes, writings, and other papers documenting the professional career of astrophysicist Rupert Wildt. The papers were donated to Yale University by Mrs. Rupert Wildt in 1977. They are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1946-1974; II. Organizations, 1949-1981; III. Personal Papers, 1898-1968; IV. Writings, 1928-1972; V. Writings of Others, 1876-1974.
The Rupert Wildt Papers are arranged in sixeen boxes. This includes one box of oversized items arranged at the end of the collection, as well as an addition recieved in 2001.
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE, 1946-1974, contains letters with colleagues and associates which detail a variety of academic and professional concerns.
SERIES II, ORGANIZATIONS, 1949-1981, contains files for several academic, scientific, and professional organizations. Files for the Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy (AURA) includes material relating to Wildt's service as president (1965-1968; 1971-1972), chairman of the board (1973-1976), and director (1958-1976). Files for the Kitt Peak National Observatory (KPNO) document Wildt's tenure as director (1965-1971) of that institution.
SERIES III, PERSONAL PAPERS, 1898-1968, includes early family documents and letters of recommendation.
SERIES IV, WRITINGS, 1928-1972, contains drafts of articles; partial bibliographies; notes and equations relating to scientific research (including oversize material in box 15); notes and teaching materials on a range of subjects including cosmochemistry, kinetics, planetochemistry, and thermodynamics; and reprints of articles.
SERIES V, WRITINGS OF OTHERS, 1876-1974, contains typescripts of work collected by Wildt and includes material from students and colleagues. Printed material includes published items of a similar nature.
Biographical / Historical
Rupert Wildt was born in Munich, Germany on June 25, 1905. Wildt arrived in the United States in 1935 and served as a research associate at Princeton (1937-1942), assistant professor at the University of Virginia (1942-1946), and a member of the Yale University faculty (1946-1976). At Yale Wildt held the positions of chairman in the Astronomy Department (1966-1968) and professor emeritus (1973-1976). He was active in several professional organizations. Wildt died in Orleans, Massachusetts on January 9, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Astronomy -- Research; Astronomy -- Study and teaching; Astrophysics; Science; Astronomers; Wildt, Rupert, 1905-1976; Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy; Kitt Peak National Observatory; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Astronomy
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1946-1974; Series I; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence arranged in two sections: General and Select. General files are arranged in chronological order. Select files are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - General
    - 1946 May - 1961 July (Box 1, Folder 1-22)
    - 1961 August - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 23-38)
  - Select
    - DeMarcus, Wendell C., 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - DeMarque, Pierre Raymond, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Edmondson, Frank K., 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Oxenius, Joachim, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Pritchett, Henry S., 1941-1966 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Street, William B., 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 44-45)
    - Waddell, John H., 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- ORGANIZATIONS, 1949-1981; Series II; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series contains an alphabetical arrangement of files according to the name of the organization.
  - Academic Press, Inc., 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - American Journal of Science, 1949-1953 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, 1949-1975 (Box 4, Folder 49-61)
  - The Astrophysical Journal, 1959-1971 (Box 4, Folder 62-63)
  - CTIO, 1963-1967 (Box 5, Folder 64-68)
  - Acta Geochímica, 1950-1967 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - ICARUS, 1961-1971 (Box 5, Folder 70-71)
  - Jupiter Conference, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 72-73)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory, 1965 January - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 74-79)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory, 1968-1981 (Box 6, Folder 80-83)
  - Liège Symposium, 1956-1963 (Box 6, Folder 84-85)
  - NASA, 1968-1971 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - NATO Advanced Study, 1965-1973 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Royal Astronomical Society, 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Springer-Verlog, Berlin, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Universidad Nacional de México, 1960-1965 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Universität Basel, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Universität München, 1953-1962 (Box 7, Folder 92-94)
  - Universität Münster, 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - University of Washington, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Yale University, 1958-1974 (Box 7, Folder 97-98)
- PERSONAL PAPERS, 1898-1968; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  This series contains general files and recommendations; each is arranged in chronological order.
  - General, 1898-1968 (Box 8, Folder 99-100)
  - Recommendations, 1958-1972 (Box 8, Folder 101)
- WRITINGS, 1928-1972; Series IV; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series contains writings arranged in five sections: Articles, Bibliographies, Notes and Equations, Notes and Teaching Materials, and Reprints of Articles.
  - Articles
    - "Cosmochemistry,", 1936-1950 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - "The Photon Diffusion Equation,", undated (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - "Radiation Transfer,", undated (Box 9, Folder 104)
    - "Thermodynamics..." II-IV, undated (Box 9, Folder 105-107)
  - Bibliographies, 1928-1972 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Notes and Equations, 1938-1954, undated (Box 9, Folder 109-133)
  - Notes and Teaching Materials
    - Fluctuations, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 134)
    - Astronomy, undated (Box 9, Folder 135-136)
    - Data of Cosmochemistry, undated (Box 9, Folder 137)
    - Externals, undated (Box 9, Folder 138)
    - General Theory of Matter, undated (Box 9, Folder 139)
    - Grey Atmosphere, undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
    - Interstellar Matter, undated (Box 9, Folder 141)
    - Literature, undated (Box 9, Folder 142)
    - Kinetics, undated (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - Mathematics, undated (Box 10, Folder 144)
    - Planetochemistry, undated (Box 10, Folder 145)
    - Solar and Stellar Chemistry, undated (Box 10, Folder 146)
    - Stress-Strain, Stationary State, undated (Box 10, Folder 147)
    - Thermodynamics, undated (Box 10, Folder 148)
    - Transfer Theory, undated (Box 10, Folder 149)
    - Variation Principles, undated (Box 10, Folder 150-151)
  - Reprints of Articles
    - 1928-1966 (Box 10, Folder 152-159)
    - 1966-1972, undated (Box 11, Folder 160-164)
- WRITINGS OF OTHERS, 1876-1974; Series V; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series contains writings arranged in two sections: Typescripts and Printed Material. Each section is arranged in chronological order.
  - Typescripts
    - Langevin, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 165)
    - Gilmore, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 166)
    - Kröll, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 167)
    - Anonymous, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 168)
    - Gal-Or, 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 169-170)
    - Anonymous, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 171)
    - Hamity, undated (Box 12, Folder 172)
    - Hayashi, undated (Box 12, Folder 173)
    - Oxenius, undated (Box 12, Folder 174)
  - Printed Material
    - 1876-1946 (Box 12, Folder 175-179)
    - 1947-1963 (Box 13, Folder 180-187)
    - 1964-1974, undated (Box 14, Folder 188-197)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL
  - Notes, equations, and computer printouts
    - Dilute equilibrium radiation, 1965, undated (Box 15, Folder 198)
    - Equilibrium radiation: thermodynamic functions, 1952, undated (Box 15, Folder 199)
    - Gray planetary atmosphere, 1961, 1965, undated (Box 15, Folder 200)
    - Gray planetary atmosphere with Kataari source function, undated (Box 15, Folder 201)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 15, Folder 202)
- Additional Material, Accession 2001-M-001
  - Correspondence
    - Kabala, Robert E. [includes draft of "The Greenhouse Effect for Inhomogeneous Finite Gray Atmospheres"], 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sagan, Carl, 1970 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ueno, Sueo, 1968 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notes and equations (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings
    - "The Geochemistry of the Atmosphere and the Constitution of the Terrestrial Planets" [fragment, draft of introductory address], 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Introductory Report: Planetary Interiors" [1962?] (Box 1, Folder 6)